Finding Aid for War of 1812 Collection
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
War of 1812 collection 1806-1860
War of 1812 collection
William L. Clements Library
2.5 linear feet
wclmss002209
The War of 1812 collection is a miscellaneous collection of approximately 300 single items relating to the War of 1812. The papers cover many aspect of the war on both the American and British sides, including naval and military operations, regimental matters, trade issues, and state and national politics relating to the war.
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
M-855 et al..
The collection is open for research.
History
The War of 1812 was a military conflict between the United States and Great Britain that lasted from 1812 to 1815. Fighting occurred primarily along the border between the United States and Canada, along the Eastern Seaboard, and throughout the South. The British and American navies fought on the Great Lakes and on the Atlantic Ocean. The Treaty of Ghent ended the war in December 1814, and the British victory at Fort Bowyer on February 12, 1815, marked the end of the fighting.
This collection is arranged chronologically.
The War of 1812 collection (approximately 300 items) contains miscellaneous letters and documents relating to the War of 1812. The papers cover many aspects of the war on both the American and British sides, including naval and military operations, regimental matters, trade issues, and state and national politics relating to the war. Item types include letters, memoranda, reports, orders, documents, reminiscences, financial documents, and returns.
Subjects:
Albany (N.Y.); Alexandria (Va.); Amherstburg (Ont.); Annapolis (Md.); Attica (N.Y.); Augusta (Me.); Baltimore (Md.)--History--War of 1812.; Bangor (Me.); Bermuda.; Blechertown (Mass.); Boston (Mass.); Buffalo (N.Y.)--History--War of 1812.; Chippewa, Battle of, Ont., 1814.; Connecticut--History--War of 1812.; Constitution (Frigate); Delaware--History--War of 1812.; Detroit (Mich.); Dover (Del.); Fairfield (Ct.); Florida--History--War of 1812.; Fort Erie (Ont.)--History--Siege, 1814.; Fredericktown (Md.); Gloucester (R.I.); Kentucky--History--War of 1812 Knoxville (Tenn.); Lake Champlain, Battle of, N.Y., 1814.; Lisbon (Portugal); London (England); Louisiana--History--War of 1812.; Lundy's Lane, Battle of, Ont., 1814.; Maine--History--War of 1812.; Maryland--History--War of 1812.; Massachusetts--History--War of 1812.; Michigan--History--War of 1812.; Military pensions--United States--War of 1812.; Mississippi--History--War of 1812.; Montréal (Québec); New Gloucester (Me.); New Jersey--History--War of 1812.; New Orleans, Battle of, New Orleans, La., 1815.; New York (N.Y.)--History--War of 1812.; New York (State)--History--War of 1812.; Newport (Ky.); Newport (R.I.); Niagara Frontier (N.Y.)--History--War of 1812.; Northwest, Old--History--War of 1812.; Ohio--History--War of 1812.; Ontario--History--War of 1812.; Paris, France.; Pennsylvania--History--War of 1812.; Philadelphia (Pa.)--History--War of 1812.; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Plattsburg, Battle of, Plattsburgh, N.Y., 1814.; Portland (Me.); President (Frigate); Quebec.; Queenston Heights, Battle of, Ont., 1812.; Sackets Harbor, Battle of, Sackets Harbor, N.Y., 1813.; Southern States--History--War of 1812.; Tennessee.; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 6th.; United States--Foreign relations--1812-1815.; United States--History--War of 1812.; United States--History--War of 1812--Naval operations.; United States. Navy--History--War of 1812.; United States. War Dept.; Vermont--History--War of 1812.; Washington D.C.; West Point (N.Y.); Wyandot Indians.
Contributors:
Armistead, George, 1780-1818.; Bainbridge, William, 1774-1833.; Biddle, James, 1783-1848.; Biddle, Nicholas, 1786-1844.; Binney, Amos, 1778-1833.; Buchanan, James, 1791-1868.; Campbell, George W. (George Washington), 1794-1869.; Clay, Green, 1757-1826.; Dearborn, Henry, 1751-1829.; Duane, William, 1760-1835.; Eustis, William, 1753-1825.; Freeling, Francis, Sir, 1764-1836.; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849.; Hull, William, 1753-1825.; Izard, George, 1777-1828.; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845.; King, Rufus, 1755-1827.; Larned, Simon, 1753-1817.; Loring, Joseph, 1767-1838.; Macomb, Alexander, 1782-1841.; Madison, James, 1751-1836.; Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1740-1823.; Monroe, James, 1758-1831.; Pinkney, lieutenant-colonel (Ninian), 1776-1825.; Prevost, George, Sir, 1767-1816.; Rodney, C. A. (Caesar Augustus), 1772-1824.; Russell, Jonathan, 1771-1832.; Tallmadge, Benjamin, 1754-1835.; Varnum, Joseph B. (Joseph Bradley), 1751-1821.; Wadsworth, Decius, 1768-1821.; Warren, John Borlase, Sir, 1753-1822.
Genre Terms:
Letters (correspondence); Memorandums.; Receipts (financial records)
- War of 1812 collection
  - 1806 April 16. Gilbert Gardner ALS to Gayer Gardner; Isle of France., 5 pages; American cargo ships have been captured by the British and condemned at Ceylon; "it has ever appeared to me that there is a want of attention in the government of the United States towards the Citizens who unfortunately are obliged to follow the seas…they are the only Class of Citizens who are any ways Exposed to personal Insults and it appears to me that they merit a greater share of Government Protection." (Box 1)
  - 1806 July 14. Henry Dearborn ALS to Barnabas Bidwell; Washington, [D.C.]., 2 pages; Regarding an incident on a schooner; he is not relying on information that he's heard concerning "the prisoners said to have been taken in the Schooners," and will wait on more authentic information. He also congratulates Bidwell, a U.S. Representative from Massachusetts, "on the improved state of the public affairs of Massachusetts."
  - [1806 to 1812?]. Nicholas Biddle AMS., 1 page; "On the Advantages of a Navy." Provides an argument on the necessity of a standing army, including the need "to protect our trade as ourselves." A navy is most needed because "we are threatened with invasion and annihilation from a country who are far superior to us in number and a navy is the only means of protecting our coast from them. A commercial country cannot subsist without a navy..."
  - 1807 June 14. Tench Coxe ALS to Caesar Augustus Rodney; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania., 3 pages; Concerning the situation with Britain, which "requires so vigilant and so close an attention…"
  - 1807 June 27. Christopher Fry ALS to Jacob Little; Norfolk, [Virginia]., 1 page; He communicates that a captain wants "his pilot…to Leave City Point with the Alfred…he shall want More Cash, & a Cable, which I shall have Made for him." He also mentions the impact of attack on the Chesapeake; it has "Left Business at a stand, Supplies to the British Ships are stopped, and we are now waiting to know what Steps will be taken by our Government, tho all is adgitation."
  - 1807 July 7. Henry Burbeck LS to Constant Freeman; Washington, [D.C.]., 2 pages; Fitting the garrison; "The present situation of affairs renders it highly necessary…to put your Garrison in the best posible state of defense…" Mentions outfitting carriages, rammers, and cannon. "And as your own reputation and that of the Regiment depends on your efforts, I feel partcularly satisfied that with the means you posess, that nothing will be wanting on your part to be prepared whenever the crisis of defending the American Flagg shall arrive."
  - 1807 November 24. William Bainbridge ALS to Charles W. Goldsborough; Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania]., 3 pages; Ready for service if the country goes to war; "I feel very anxious for the arrival of the Revenge, in order for the Government to ascertain wither Peace or War is to be the fate of our Country…in the event of the latter I trust they [his services] would be found usefull to our Country & honourable to myself." Discussing issues concerning pay.
  - 1808 February 6. Peter DeWitt ALS to John DeWitt; New York., 3 pages; Letter to his father regarding hardships caused by the embargo; "our national prospects are daily becoming more and more gloomy…mercantile business more and more declining." He fears the consequences of war with England; "a war with england is as confidently apprehended as ever peace was desired--and that England will not permit us to trade with either of the other European Countries is not pretended to be doubted." Discusses matters relating to his father's western lands.
  - 1808 March 8. Peter DeWitt ALS to John DeWitt; New York., 6 pages; Hardships caused by the embargo; he has heard that the embrago may not be taken off "in this city…less than one or two years." The American government will have it so that the "the people of this Country shall suffer all the disadvantages of War & not reap...the advantages of peace." Mentions the specifics of a duel, and feels that it is advantageous to settle in the Ohio country.
  - 1808 April 19. Henry Dearborn LS to Israel Smith; War Department., 2 pages; Regarding a violation of embargo in Vermont; "you will perceive that a violation of the Embargo laws, is contemplated on the borders of the lake, within the State of Vermont...I am directed by the President of the United States...to request that you will afford such further assistance by the Militia...for suppressing any unlawful combination with an intention, of violating the laws of the United States, by opposing those laying an Embargo, passed in the present of Congress."
  - 1808 October 20. Henry Dearborn ALS to Henry Alexander Scammell Dearborn; Washington, [D.C.]., 4 pages; Discusses Madison’s election and relations with Britain; "I preceive there will be no other Alternative but War, or a continuance of the Embargo, with such additional provisions for a strict & ridged execution of it…the honor and character of the Nation must forbid any relaxations in our measures until the European Nations shall be disposed to respect our sacred rights."
  - 1808 November 13. William Eustis ALS to [Richard Cutts]; Boston, [Massachusetts]., 1 page; Regarding the benefits of employing seamen during embargo; "It is intimated to me that there is a probability of the Embargo's being continued. If that should be the case is it not desirable that the seamen...should be engaged in the Service." Speaks on the benefits of employing these men, including the fact that they will not be idle, which contributes to riots in seaport towns. The "Govr. continues & is able to do business.--it is said he will hold out & die with honor" [referring to James Sullivan, who would die on December 10, 1808].
  - 1808 December 9. John Howe ALS to Sir Francis Freeling; Washington., 8 pages; Regarding the political situation and the lack of an American Navy; "I believe Mr. Madison is at present convinced that if he plunges America into a War with England, it will involve the Country in such a scene of espence and misery, or will injure eventually his popularity, and make his administration painful in the extreme." He states that a war with France might be preferable because New England is hostile to Madison "and who have no objection to a War with France."
  - 1808 December 20. Ezekiel Bacon ALS to A. Bishop; Washington, [D.C.]., 3 pages; Some are looking to war; he encloses a report from Mr. [Albert] Gallatin, "I think his views against to War…"
  - 1809 February 4. William Bainbridge ALS to James Biddle; Washington, [D.C.]., 1 page; Regarding naval matters; appointment to second Lieutenant and reassignment to a new ship. Captain [Isaac] Hull has taken command of the Chesapeake. Bainbridge sends a message to Biddle's father.
  - 1809 February 13. Amos A. Evans ALS to John Evans and Mary Alexander Evans; New Orleans, [Louisiana]., 4 pages; Letter from son serving on a ship; "I have not heard a word from Elkton [Maryland] since my departure." Gives a description of the houses and buildings around New Orleans; "they remind me of old castles I have read of in novels." Mentions the commercial importance of the city.
  - 1809 June 15. Amos A. Evans ALS to John Evans and Mary [Alexander] Evans; New Orleans, [Louisiana]., 3 pages; Letter from son serving on a ship, mentions the embargo; "the news of the removal of the Embargo hindered it from being a proftable one…the situation of many Americans as well as Spaniards & French in the Floridas was truly wretched." Discusses matters relating to the United States' differences with Great Britain and issues regarding search and imprisonment.
  - 1810 February 24. [Unknown writer] Ms., 13 pages; Proceedings and condemnation of ship Aristides (in French).
  - 1810 July 18 and 1810 July 19. Joseph A. Ellery DS to William Dolliver, Jr.; Lisbon., 3 pages; Document sworn before William Jarvis, American Consul to Lisbon, testifying to William Dolliver being an American citizen.
  - 1811 February 18. M.F.F. Berkeley, Baron Fitzhardinge LS to George Berkeley; Tagus River., 2 pages; Regarding impressment of four men; "The Men names in the Margin, claimed by Americans by Mr Green, Deputy Consul of the United States of America, are now on board His Majesty's Ship under my Command." One of the men was "impressed from a Portuguese Merchant Ship, not being on her Muster Rolls; the two latter were sent on board...from His Majesty's Ship...and have American Protections."
  - After 1811 May 17. John O. Creighton AD., 3 pages; Regarding the Little Belt Affair, including eyewitness accounts of the skirmish between an American frigate and British sloop off the coast of North Carolina (with a six-page contemporary folio copy).
  - 1811 May 31 to 1811 June 30. United States Army Sixth Infantry Regiment. Pr. Document., 2 pages; Muster Roll of Capt. George Nelson's company in the United States Sixth Infantry Regiment.
  - 1811 June 29. Sat. Clark ALS to Isaac Clark; Annapolis, [Maryland]., 2 pages; Regarding the Little Belt Incident; "You have probably seen Capt. Hinghams Letters giving account of the affair of the Little Belt which is totally different from that of Comod. Rogers. It is anxiously believed here that the affair will result in War."
  - 1811 December 16. Alexander Macomb ALS to Samuel Champlain; Fredericktown, Maryland., 4 pages; Regarding difficulty of getting promotion in the army; "The Doctors letter I enclosed…with Such remarks as were I deemed proper & I trust according with his wished to procure promotion in the present army." He senses "much difficulty as every one seems jealous of his own particular rights." He mentions that Congress is talking about raising 25,000 additional troops.
  - 1812 January 11. Hughes and Dean Pr. letter to Brown and Ives; Liverpool, [England]., 3 pages; Regarding tensions between U.S. and Britain and anticipating the U.S. declaration of war. Discuses matters pertaining to cotton, turpentine, wheat, flour, and other crops. Includes a table with information pertaining to the stock and prices of American, Russian, and West Indian produce.
  - 1812 January 16. Benjamin Tallmadge ALS; Washington, [D.C.]., 4 pages; Regarding the sentiment in Congress for war against Britain; "The Great Question now before us is the War with G. Britain. If we could draw any Safe Conclusions from the noisy, blurbering Speeches of our Kentucky & Tenesee Brethren…we might as well Say that war...[might] be the result." [presumably referencing War Hawks like Henry Clay and Felix Grundy.] He also mentions those opposed to a potential war on the facts that it would take too many men and too much money.
  - 1812 February 26. Jonathan Russell ALS to Joel Barlow; London, [England]., 3 pages; News from America makes him suspect hostilities; "The information received from America gives reason to expect measures of hostility towards this country - altho it is not here believed that any such measures will be adopted…we are considered incapable of making any very formidable effort..." He makes brief reference to circumstances surrounding the British Regency; "The famous epoch of the cessation of the restrictions on the Regent [George IV] has passed..."
  - 1812 March 24. Jonathan Russell ALS to Joel Barlow; London, [England]., 4 pages; Expresses the inability to having a philosophicae apparatus shipped from America because of embargo; he had requested of [Isaac] Hull's officers that sent boxes to the United States aboard the USS Constitution, which Hull refused because it was merchandize. He has made further arrangements regarding his items.
  - 1812 May 3. William Eustis ALS; War Department., 3 pages; Building up of Army, including matters pertaining to stores and barracks. "The whole labour of this Department is still incumbent on the Secretary of War…Congress have passed an act authorising two additional Secretaries, assistant I should have said: and I will thank you to name two or three in whom you should have confidence."
  - 1812 June 10. Jonathan Snowden ALS to Joseph Bloomfield; West Point, [New York]., 1 page; Regarding the amount of arms ready for service; "at this store there is only 379 stand of French arms…that is fit for service and they have been used formerly Should you think of calling for them, it will be necessary that you obtain an order for that purpose from the secretary of war to inable me to deliver them..."
  - 1812 June 15. United States ADS to William Kelley; Urbana, [Ohio]., 1 page; Receipt from U.S. government of $30 payment for "one Pack Horse for Ohio Volunteers under command of Brigr. Genl. Wm Hull…Recd. of James Taylor," a United States agent.
  - 1812 June 26. William Eustis ALS to Col. Worthington., 1 page; Appointment of general Indian Council at Brownstown, expects Tecumseh and other chiefs to attend; "By a Letter from General Hull it appears that he has appointed a general Indian Council at Brownstown at which he expects Tecumseh & the other chiefs from the Wabash & the Delawares...The council to be held in 40 Days from June 9th the date of the Letter."
  - 1812 July 5. George Cranfield Berkeley LS to John Jeffery; Lisbon, Portugal., 2 pages; Thanking the merchants of the British Factory at Lisbon for an address given to him when he left. He references his retirement as Lord High Admiral of the Portuguese Navy and public life; "my regret...of departing from this Station, is considerably lessened by a knowledge of the Character of my successor, being confident you will find in his measures an Equal attention to the public Interests...I beg leave to acknowledge my Thanks for the honor, you have conferr'd upon me." (Box 2)
  - 1812 July 8. John Hubbard ALS to Ebenezer Huntington; Hamden, [Connecticut]., 3 pages; Description of uniforms for Connecticut Militia.
  - 1812 July 9. [William] Hull ALS to James Taylor; Detroit, [Michigan]., 2 pages; Request for pack horses to be transported to John H. Piatt. At the bottom Piatt writes that he "Received of James Taylor…forty pack Horses Detroit July 10th 1812 Seventy bags. thirty five pack Saddles…"
  - 1812 August 1. [Henry] Bathurst LS to The Officer administering the Government New Brunswick [George Stracey Smyth]; Downing Street, [London, England]., 2 pages; Circular that all American ships are to be detained; "I transmit to you...a Copy of an Order of His Royal Highness the Prince Regent…directing that all Ships and Vessels belonging to the United States of America...within or which may hereafter arrive within the limits of any of the Ports, Harbours or Roads of any of His Majesty's Forts or Settlements abroad, should be detained...with all Persons and Effects on board the said Ships and Vessels."
  - 1812 August 16 - 1812 September 1. Northwest Army DS copy, signed., 8 pages; [Michigan] Territory. 8 pages. Protest against Britain’s retention of private property taken at the surrender of Detroit, with list of property in question. Includes protests by James Taylor and James Findley.
  - 1812 August 27. Nathan Sage DS., 2 pages; Certified account of Peter Buell Porter, Quartermaster General of New York State, with Henry Taft for $6. The receipt is signed by Taft.
  - 1812 August 28. Henry B. Armstrong ALS to Cushion; Greenbush., 1 page; Forwarding him a commission; "I seize this opportunity of forwarding to you a Commission which I received June the 30th 1812."
  - 1812 August 30. James Monroe ALS; Washington, [D.C.]., 1 page; Discusses an appointment and mentions that "disaster at Detroit." This compels him to write about the "the marshal character which must be removed."
  - 1812 August 31. John Hale ALS to Sir William Amherst; Quebec., 5 pages; Report on Hull's surrender at Detroit and a map of Detroit
  - 1812 September 4. Frederick Spofford ALS to Charles Spofford; Deer Isle, [Maine]., 1 page; Discusses trade conditions in war time and various voyages to Boston and Lisbon. "The War measures of our Government have almost put a stop to business in this part of the country, it is almost impossible to collect debts or do any business to advantage…it will wax worse instead of better..."
  - 1812 September 5. Henry Dearborn ALS to William Eustis; Greenbush., 1 page; Discusses the return of Captain Pickney from Montreal; "at Montreal he was allowed to pass freely about…Capt McClary accompanied him from Burlington to Montreal." Mentions Governor-General Prevost, Detroit, "and the prospect of hostilities being commenced on the frontier."
  - 1812 September 9.. R[eturn] J[onathan] Meigs ALS to Fort Manary Commanding Officer; Urbana, [Ohio]., 1 page; Governor Meigs directs rations to be issued to families who fled River Raisin; "You will see that Rations are issued to Andrew Race's family & the other families in Lick have fled from River Raisin…"
  - [1812] September 10. Return Jonathan Meigs ALS to Col. [Alexander] Enos; Urbana, [Ohio]., 2 pages; Discusses the movements of General Harrison and stationing of troops; "Gen: Harrison is gone to Fort Wayne with 3,000 Troops chiefly Kentuckians--2,000 Kentuckians are near Dayton-I have here 1,000 Men…waiting for Instructions from the Sec at War." He mentions Col. Enos's possible command on the frontiers.
  - 1812 September 12. Alexander J. Dallas ALS to John Steele., 2 pages; Pertaining to goods seized by the government under the Non Importation Acts. All goods that had been imported from Britain subsequent to the revocation of the Orders in Council can not be seized and must be returned; "all goods, imported in any vessel, sailing from England, subsequent to the alledged revocation of the Orders in Council...shall be restored to the respective claimants, upon Bond, in the manner prescribed, by law for cases of forfeiture under the Revenue system."
  - 1812 September 12. John Hale ALS to Sir William Amherst; Quebec., 2 pages; Report on Hull's surrender at Detroit.
  - 1812 September 12 to 1812 October 14. United States Army 7 DsS., 2 pages; Receipts for horses purchased from J. Witmore & Company.
  - 1812 September 15. Gilbert Gardner ALS to Gayer Gardner; Chesapeake Bay., 3 pages; Embarking on commercial voyage despite risks of war time; he is bound for Spain. Discusses commercial matters and real estate prospects.
  - 1812 September 18. Amos Stoddard ALS to James R. Butler; Pittsburgh, [Pennsylvania]., 1 page; Orders to march to Northwest Army; "It is the direction of the Secy of war, that you march your company to the northwestern Army. You will accordingly proceed with all convenient dispatch- and on your arrival report yourself to the Officer commanding that army."
  - 1812 September 19. Arad Joy ALS to Ira Joy; Camp at Manchester, near Niagara Falls, [New York]., 4 pages; Describes living conditions in camp; "I am in Good Health our Regiment remain in Good Health not one yet So Sick as to go to the hospital…" Comments on life as paymaster and the routine of closing down camp at night.